Moving on to skeletal muscle, the first disorder that we're going to discuss is dermatomyositis.
Now the name here tells you a lot.
You've got myositis, which is inflammation of the muscle,
and dermato, which implies that you have inflammation of the skin.
And so this is going to be an inflammatory disorder of both the skin and the skeletal muscle.
The etiology is not known, but what is particularly high yield
is that some cases of dermatomyositis are associated with carcinoma,
for example, gastric carcinoma.
Board examiners like you to know that if a patient presents with dermatomyositis,
you need to consider the possibility of an underlying carcinoma, especially in the stomach.
The clinical features of dermatomyositis are that you'll get bilateral proximal muscle weakness,
that's high yield, and by proximal muscle weakness,
the way by which the patients would present would classically be they will say that they can't comb their hair,
because when you raise your arm to comb your hair, you need to use the shoulders,
and they can't climb the stairs.
Now, late in the disease, they can develop distal involvement,
but again, the hallmark is proximal muscle weakness.
In addition, we would expect to see skin changes, and there are three key skin changes that you look for.
Number one is a rash of the upper eyelids, and this gives a little bit of a purple discoloration to the upper eyelids.
Number two, a malar rash, and I think that this is particularly high yield,
because board examiners like to go after this,
and the reason they like to go after it is because you classically associate a malar rash with lupus,
but you need to remember that you can also have a malar rash in dermatomyositis,
and that, again, is particularly high yield, because it's one of those knee jerks that, you know,
once you see the word malar rash, you think you're done, and you pick lupus.
However, actually, you were dealing with dermatomyositis.
And the third rash would be these red papules on the elbow, knuckles, and knees,
which are also known as groton lesions.
And again, so again, you're going to have muscle weakness plus some skin finding.
On laboratory exam, the patients will have an increased creatinine kinase.
Creatinine kinase is an enzyme present in muscle, so when it's damaged,
so when muscle is damaged, this will leak out into the blood.
You'll have a positive ANA with an anti-JO1 antibody.
A JO1 antibody is very important.
It's the hallmark of this disease.
Be careful about the positive ANA.
If they tell you on the board exam that there's a positive ANA and a malar rash,
don't go after lupus until you also have a confirmatory test,
like a double-stranded DNA antibody.
Or, if you have an anti-JO1 antibody, then think about dermatomyositis.
The hallmark and one of the defining features of this disease
is that you have perimesial inflammation with perifascicular atrophy.
Now, in order to understand that, let's go back and remind ourselves
this is the muscle fascicle.
And the fascicle is made up of a bunch of individual fibers.
Now, the connective tissue that sits out here at the edge of the fascicle,
this is called the perimesium.
And the connective tissue that sits in between the fibers,
this is called the endomysium.
Now, what happens in dermatomyositis is that you get inflammation at the perimesium,
so out at the edge of the muscle fascicle, which then results in perifascicular atrophy,
or atrophy of the muscle with inflammation out at the edge.
This is very high yield because it helps to distinguish dermatomyositis from another entity
that we're going to talk about, which is polymyositis,
because in polymyositis, you're going to have endomysial inflammation.
And the way I remember this, i.e., that is it endomysial or perimesial,
is that the perimesium is out at the edge, and so it's closer to the skin.
And so, in dermatomyositis, you're going to have perimesial inflammation,
which is closer to the skin, and so therefore,
it sort of matches with the concept of dermatomyositis.
Now, again, that's just one way to remember it, but I think it's helpful.
Here's an image to highlight the same principle.
This is a muscle fascicle,
and you'll notice that you've got inflammation out in the connective tissue
at the edge of the muscle fascicle,
resulting in some atrophy of the muscle cells.
Now, notice that this is the normal size of the muscle cell,
and can you notice that these here are smaller,
hence they've become atrophic.
And so, again, perimesial inflammation
with perifascicular atrophy of the muscle.
And so the way by which I remember this is,
let's assume the skin is way out here, way above in this section,
then this would be sort of closer to the skin,
and that's how I remember that it's part of dermatomyositis.
One final point concerning dermatomyositis,
and that is that the treatment is corticosteroids.
Of course, this is an inflammatory disorder,
and corticosteroids would limit the inflammation.
Polyomyositis is an inflammatory disorder of skeletal muscle.
It resembles dermatomyositis,
especially with the proximal muscle weakness.
However, the skin will not be involved.
So you will not see malar rash,
you will not see a purplish rash of the upper eyelids,
and you will not see Groton's lesions
on the knees and the elbows, for example.
In addition, one key distinction is that in polymyositis,
you get endomysial inflammation with necrotic muscle fibers.
Again, this endomysial is particularly high yield,
so here you've got the muscle fascicle
made up of a bunch of fibers, as I've already illustrated.
This was the perimesium.
This is the endomysium.
And so what's going to happen in polymyositis
is that you'll have inflammation scattered
throughout this muscle fascicle
between all of the fibers.
Again, you'll have endomysial inflammation.
Moving on to X-linked muscular dystrophy,
this is a degenerative disorder characterized by muscle wasting,
but the most important and most high yield point
concerning this disorder
is that you get replacement of skeletal muscle
by adipose tissue.
In fact, that's really what's meant by dystrophy.
And so X-linked muscular dystrophy,
replacement of skeletal muscle by adipose tissue.
Now, it's high yield to know
that this is due to deletions of dystrophin,
and there's a few points that I'd like to make clear,
all of which show up on exams.
Number one, it is due to deletions of dystrophin.
This is also known as Duchenne's muscular dystrophy,
and remember that Duchenne's is also due to deletions,
and so they both begin with a D.
The second point that you have to know
is that mutations are often spontaneous in this gene.
Now, the reason this happens
is because this gene is the largest gene in the human genome,
and so therefore, because of its large size,
there's an increased risk for spontaneous mutations,
and the third point is that dystrophin
is an anchor molecule
that angles the muscle cytoskeleton
to the extracellular matrix.
Now, imagine if this is a muscle cell,
and you've got all of your filaments in it,
then dystrophin is sort of this linker molecule
that allows you to then interact
with the extracellular matrix.
It's one of many proteins that do so,
but it is an essential protein, again,
that links the muscle cytoskeleton
to the extracellular matrix.
Patients with Duchenne's X-linked muscular dystrophy,
they present with proximal muscle weakness
classically at one year of age,
so the disease begins proximally,
for example, in the thigh and the hip,
and then eventually progresses
to involve the distal muscle.
Now, the hallmark of this sequence
is calf pseudohypertrophy.
Let me just explain this.
So at about one year of age,
the child is learning how to walk.
Now, when the child is learning how to walk,
at the same time,
the proximal muscles are going to start becoming weak.
When the proximal muscles become weak,
the child is then going to put more force
on the calf muscle in order to walk.
And as they put more force on the calf muscle,
the calf muscle is going to undergo hypertrophy.
Now, over time, the disease will progress
and then come distally.
And as it comes distally,
it's going to hit the calf,
and when it hits the hypertrophied calf,
it's going to convert the calf
from muscle into fat,
because that's the hallmark of muscular dystrophy.
And so then,
it'll look like the calf muscle is big.
However, were you to put your hand on it,
it would actually be full of fat.
So that's why they call it pseudohypertrophy.
The calf does look big.
However, it's just really full of fat instead of muscle.
In addition,
the creatinine kinase will be elevated.
And again,
the reason that the creatinine kinase is elevated
is that you have damage to muscle cells,
and creatinine kinase is an enzyme
present within muscle cells.
Death in this disorder results from cardiac
or respiratory failure.
Eventually, the myocardium or the diaphragm
will become involved,
resulting in cardiac or respiratory failure.
And again,
the myocardium is commonly involved.
Becker muscular dystrophy
is the exact same disease
as Duchenne X-linked muscular dystrophy.
However,
remember that in Duchenne's,
you had a deletion of dystropin,
whereas in Becker's,
you have a mutation of dystropin.
Now this mutation allows for some of the protein
to be produced,
and so therefore,
you get clinically milder disease.
So it's very similar.
However,
the patients have clinically milder disease.
And again,
the hallmark would be
focal replacement of skeletal muscle with fat
and also muscular weakness.
Moving on to the neuromuscular junction,
there's two disorders we want to cover.
However,
before we do that,
we need a little bit of background.
So let's remind ourselves
that the neuromuscular junction has a nerve.
It contains acetylcholine,
and it has a calcium channel here
that, when open,
allows for the release of acetylcholine.
There is also a muscle plate
with acetylcholine receptors,
and it's these receptors
that bind acetylcholine
and then cause firing of the muscle.
Now the first disorder is myasthenia gravis,
and in this disorder,
you have an antibody
against these receptors.
The antibody does not destroy the receptors.
It merely competes with acetylcholine
at the level of the receptor.
So what's going to happen
is the first time you have firing of the nerve
and you release acetylcholine,
let's imagine that 50 molecules
of acetylcholine are released.
They'll compete with the antibody,
kick off the antibody,
and allow for a proper contraction of the muscle.
However,
with rapid contraction of the muscle,
you'll have rapid firing of the nerve,
and you'll only be able to release,
for example,
the next time 40 molecules,
and then,
for example,
the next time 30 molecules
of acetylcholine,
et cetera,
until you get to the point
where you're releasing fewer molecules
of acetylcholine
with each contraction.
Now,
once,
now as that occurs,
and for example,
you're only releasing 10,
that's going to decrease
the ability of acetylcholine
to compete with the antibody,
and so over time,
with repeated contractions,
you actually get muscle weakness.
Then if there's rest,
you build up additional acetylcholine,
again,
then you,
you contract the muscle,
and then you release 50 again,
which can easily compete
with this,
with these antibodies.
So this is the hallmark
of myasthenia gravis.
Now,
another important point here
is that when you give the patient
anticholinaristerase agents,
the symptoms improve.
The idea is
that the anticholinaristerase agents
allow the acetylcholine
that's coming from the nerve
to last for a longer time,
and if it lasts for a longer time,
it'll better be able to compete
against these antibodies,
and therefore,
it'll improve the symptoms.
So with that background in mind,
let's move on to myasthenia gravis.
So as your text states,
this is an autoantibody
against the postsynaptic
acetylcholine receptor
at the neuromuscular junction,
more commonly seen in women.
Of course,
it's an autoimmune disease.
Clinically,
the features will be muscle weakness
that worsens with use.
Again,
you're releasing less and less
acetylcholine
as you rapidly use the muscle,
and it improves with rest,
and that's because
if you give the neuromuscular junction
time to rest,
additional acetylcholine
will build up
within that nerve.
Classically,
it involves the eyes,
leading to ptosis
and double vision,
and that's an important hallmark
that would show up
in a clinical vignette.
The symptoms will improve
with anticholonesterase agents.
Again,
the longer acetylcholine
is present
in the neuromuscular junction,
the better it will compete
with those antibodies,
and very high yield,
it's associated
with thymic hyperplasia
or thymoma.
This shows up
on the board exams often,
and this is important
because if there's thymic hyperplasia
or thymoma,
and you remove the thymus,
the patient's symptoms
will improve.
And so again,
this is particularly high yield
that the patients
can have thymic hyperplasia
or thymoma.
Eaton-Lambert syndrome
is when you have an antibody
against the presynaptic calcium channels
at the neuromuscular junction.
Now recall that
if this was the nerve
and this was the plate here,
there was a calcium channel here
that when open
resulted in the release
of acetylcholine.
So imagine
if you have an antibody
against the calcium channel,
you're not going to be able
to release acetylcholine,
and so you're going to get
muscle weakness.
Now this is classically seen
as a perineoplastic syndrome,
most commonly due
to small cell carcinoma.
Again, you'll get impaired
release of acetylcholine,
and that'll then result
in muscle weakness.
Now very high yield
to note in this disorder
that the proximal muscles
are involved
and the eyes
are usually spared.
In addition,
the anticholonesterase agents
will not improve the symptoms.
And of course,
because if you're not able
to release acetylcholine,
then you're not going
to be able
to improve the symptoms
with anticholonesterase agents.
And so we say
that in Lambert-Eaton syndrome,
you have antibodies
against the presynaptic
calcium channels
at the neuromuscular junction.
It's a perineoplastic syndrome
related to small cell carcinoma,
and it impairs
release of acetylcholine.
The proximal muscles
will be weak,
and the weakness
will improve with use.
Let me just quickly explain this.
The reason why
the weakness improves
with use
is that you've got
an antibody here
competing with the calcium channel.
And so what's going to happen
is the more you fire this nerve,
the more there's going
to be a gradient
trying to force calcium in.
And so again,
the more you use the nerve,
the more the pressure
to force calcium in,
and you'll be able
to then kick off
this receptor.
And so the muscle weakness
will actually improve
with use.
And the eyes are usually spared,
particularly high yield.
Again,
anticholonesterase agents
don't improve the symptoms,
and if you remove the tumor,
the perineoplastic syndrome
will disappear.
The final section
in this chapter
is soft tissue tumors.
This is going to be
a very brief overview
of just a couple tumors.
The first is lipoma.
Lipo means fat,
and oma means mass,
so this is a benign tumor
of adipose tissue.
Important to know,
it's the most common
benign soft tissue tumor
in adults.
Liposarcoma.
Lipo means fat,
and sarcoma means
malignant mesenchymal tumor.
So this is a malignant tumor
of adipose tissue.
Important to know,
it's the most common
malignant soft tissue tumor
in adults.
Also,
the board examiners
like you to know
that the lipoblast
is the characteristic cell.
So if they tell you
that there's a mass
and the pathology report
says that lipoblasts
are present,
you're thinking
about liposarcoma.
Rhabdomyosarcoma.
Rhabdomyo means skeletal muscle,
and oma refers to mass,
and so this is a benign tumor
of skeletal muscle.
Now,
you can also have
a cardiac rhabdomyoma
and very high yield
to recall,
and we talked about this
in the cardiac lectures,
that this is associated
with tuberous sclerosis.
Rhabdomyosarcoma,
again,
rhabdomyo,
skeletal muscle,
and sarcoma,
malignant mesenchymal tumor.
So this is a malignant tumor
of skeletal muscle.
Important to know,
it's the most common
malignant soft tissue tumor
in children.
Most common malignant
soft tissue tumor
in children.
The characteristic cell
is called a rhabdomyoblast.
Board examiners like you
to know that this cell
is Desmond positive.
The most common sight
is the head and neck.
However,
in a young girl,
especially around
the age of five,
the vagina
is a classic sight.
And remember,
we talked about
a disorder
in the gynae lectures
called sarcoma botrytes,
which I told you
at that point
was also an embryonal
rhabdomyosarcoma.
This was the young girl
with a grape-like mass
protruding from the vagina.
And I told you
that characteristic
on biopsy,
you would see rhabdomyoblast
with striations
within the cells
and then cells
that were
Desmond positive
as well.
And so this
is what I'm referring to
when I say that
the vagina
is a classic sight
in young girls.
And that's probably
the highest yield
rhabdomyosarcoma
that would show up
on a board exam.
And that concludes
both the section
and the chapter.